Register of the Joseph Freeman papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS (PROSE), 1912-1965
  - "Against Imperialist War," New Masses, Printed copy, 1932 August (Folder 18)
  - "The Cultural Revolution," Soviet Russia Today, Printed copy, 1932 September (Folder 19)
  - "Where There's Smoke," New Republic, Review of Isaac Don Levine, Red Smoke. Typescript, printed copy, clipping, flyer, reply by Levine, and correspondence with Malcolm Cowley, 1932 October 19. (Folder 20)
  - "Toward a Classless Society," New Masses, Printed copy, 1932 November (Folder 21)
  - Letter to the editor, New Republic, Reply to comments by Isaac Don Levine on Freedman's review, "Where There's Smoke." Printed copy and printed copy of Levine's comments, 1932 November 16. (Folder 22)
  - Radio speech, WRNY Radio (New York City), Typescripts, 1932 December 13. (Folder 23)
  - "Greenwich Village Types," International Literature, Printed copy (in Russian), 1933. (Folder 24)
  - "Poetry and Critical Works," International Literature, Obituary for Gary Allen Potamkin. Printed copy (in Russian), 1933. (Folder 25)
  - "Techno-Ballyhoo," New Masses, Typescript and printed copy, 1933 January (Folder 26)
  - "Machado's End," New Masses, Printed copy, 1933 February (Folder 27)
  - "Appearance and Reality," Student Review, Printed copy, 1933 April. (Folder 28)
  - "The Background of German Fascism," New Masses, Letter and printed copies, 1933, 1933 April. (Folder 29)
  - "Who Owns America?" New Masses, Printed copy, 1933 April. (Folder 30)
  - "Should Critics Know Anything?" New Masses, Printed copy, 1933 May. (Folder 31)
  - "Revolution and Art," Nation, Letter to the editor relating to an article by Charles Yale Harrison. Typescripts and printed copy, 1933 May 10. (Folder 32)
  - "Mexico," Typescript, 1933 July. (Folder 33)
  - Letter to the editor (?), New Republic, Response to Edmund Wilson, "Paradoxes in Detroit." Typescript, printed copy of Wilson's article, proof copy of a reply by Diego Rivera, printed copies of subsequent responses by Wilson, and correspondence between Wilson and Freeman, 1933., 1933 August 16. (Folder 34)
    SEE ALSO: "Painting and Politics: The Case of Diego Rivera," 1932 Feb. and SUBJECT FILE/Rivera, Diego
  - "Anti-Imperialist Delegation Leaves Today for Havana," Daily Worker, Printed copy, 1933 November 9. (Box 70, Folder 1)
  - "Literature Award Goes to Bunin, an Anti-Soviet Writer," Daily Worker, Printed copy, 1933 November 10. (Folder 2)
  - "1918-1933," Daily Worker, Printed copy, 1933 November 11. (Folder 3)
  - "Our Own Toe-Twisters," Daily Worker, Printed copy, 1933 November 25. (Folder 4)
  - "What a World!" Daily Worker, Substitute columnist for Mike Gold. Typescripts, printed copies, and correspondence, 1933, 1933 November-December (Folder 5-7)
  - "'Peace On Earth': The First Theatre Union Production," Daily Worker, Printed copy, 1933 December 2. (Folder 8)
  - Biographical sketch on Charles Ruthenberg, Typescript and correspondence, 1933-1934 (Folder 9)
  - "The Liberal Viewpoint in 1920," Typescript, 1934. (Folder 10)
  - "Literary Visions of Fascism," Typescript, 1934. (Folder 11)
  - "Notes on Upton Sinclair," Typescript, 1934. (Folder 12)
  - "Poetry, Politics, and Party," Typescript, 1934. (Folder 13)
  - Statement, Relates to the controversy over the mural painted by Diego Rivera for the Rockefeller Center. Typescript, 1934 February 12. (Folder 14)
  - "Empire of the Sun," New Masses, Typescript and printed copy, 1934 April 17. (Folder 15)
  - "Comic Strip," 1934 May. Review of Tess Slesinger, The Unpossessed. Typescript, clipping, and letter (Folder 16)
  - "Ferryboat and Warship," Typescript, 1934 May. (Folder 17)
  - Untitled relating to Nazi propaganda in the United States, Daily Worker, Typescript and clippings, 1934, 1934 May 9. (Folder 18)
  - "Tampa, Florida," Daily Worker, Series of articles relating to a tobacco workers strike. Typescript drafts, letters, and printed copies, 1934, 1934 May 10-15. (Folder 19)
  - "Mrs. Grady Is Here Again," Typescripts, 1934 May 23. (Folder 20)
  - "The Birds," Dynamo, Typescript and printed copy, 1934 Summer. (Folder 21)
  - "Criticism--or Spleen?" Typescript, 1934 June. (Folder 22)
  - "Critics in Mufti," New Masses, Printed copy, 1934 June 5. (Folder 23)
  - "Marx on Literature," Typescript and notes, 1934 July. (Folder 24)
  - Article on Walt Whitman, Daily Worker, Typescripts and printed copy, 1934 July 7. (Folder 25)
  - "Soviet Literature and the United States," Pravda, Printed copy (in Russian), 1934 July 8. (Folder 26)
  - "A Tribute to Robert Minor," Daily Worker, Printed copy, 1934 August 16. (Folder 27)
  - "Elmer Rice," New Theatre, Typescript and printed copy, 1934 September (Folder 28)
  - "Ivory Towers--White and Red," New Masses, Typescripts, printed copy, and letters, 1934, 1934 September 11. (Folder 29)
  - "U.S. Writers Describe Influence of Bolshevik Revolution on Their Work," Daily Worker, Printed copy, 1934 September 20. (Folder 30)
  - "Nice People," Typescript, 1934 October (Folder 31)
  - "The Meaning of Fascism," New Masses, Printed copy, 1934 October 2. (Box 71, Folder 1)
  - "A Specific Case," Typescript, 1934 October 14. (Folder 2)
  - "You Can Fight Here," New Masses, Review of Edward Newhouse, You Can't Sleep Here. Typescript (incomplete), printed copy, and letters by Newhouse, 1934 December 11 (Folder 3)
  - "Homage to Lenin," Typescript, circa 1935 (Folder 4)
  - "An American Literary Heritage," Typescripts, 1935. (Folder 5)
  - "Assignments to Utopia," Typescript, 1935. (Folder 6)
  - "The Cult of the Ego," Typescript, 1935. (Folder 7)
  - "Havana and Yucatan (1929)," Typescript, 1935. (Folder 8)
  - "The Lineage of the Moon: A Note on Pilnyak," Typescript, 1935. (Folder 9)
  - "Mammonart," Typescript, 1935. (Folder 10)
  - "Mexican Story (1929)," Typescript, 1935. (Folder 11)
  - "Mexico: First Week (1929)," Typescript, 1935. (Folder 12)
  - "A Note on Ethics," Typescript, 1935. (Folder 13)
  - "A Note on Good and Evil," Typescript, 1935. (Folder 14)
  - Proletarian Literature, 1935. Typescript preface, newsletter, printed matter, reviews, notes, and letters, 1935-1938 (Folder 15)
  - Review of Frederick L. Schuman, The Nazi Dictatorship, Typescript and correspondence with Edward Dahlberg and another, 1935, circa 1935. (Box 72, Folder 1)
  - "Twilight of the Idols," Comments on article by Robert Briffault, "The Essential Life of Christianity." Typescript and printed copy of Briffault's article, 1935. (Folder 2)
  - "Karl Billinger's Fatherland," New Masses, Review of Karl Billinger, Fatherland. Typescripts and printed copy, 1935 April 9. (Folder 3)
  - "The Tradition of American Revolutionary Literature," New Masses, Typescript and printed copy, 1935 May 7. (Folder 4)
  - "The Road to Freedom," Soviet Russia Today, Review of Anna Louise Strong, I Change Worlds. Typescript and printed copy, 1935 June. (Folder 5)
  - "Mask, Image and Truth," Partisan Review, Typescript and printed copy, 1935 July-August (Folder 6)
  - "From Colonial Oppression to Socialist Construction," Communist, Review of Joshua Kunitz, Dawn Over Samarkand. Typescript and printed copy, 1935 August (Folder 7)
  - "Homage to Barbusse," New Masses, Typescript and printed copy, 1935 September 10 (Folder 8)
  - "Shaw and Mussolini," New Masses, Typescript and printed copy, 1935 October 29 (Folder 9)
  - "Russia Must Crush Reaction," Current Controversy, Typescript and printed copy, 1935 December (Folder 10)
  - "Lenin, Kolchak, and Lansing," Typescript (incomplete), circa 1936 (Folder 11)
  - American Testament, 1936
    - General. Preface, outlines, cast of characters, radio broadcast transcript, and reader's report by Robert Cantwell, 1935-1936 (Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1935-1963 (Folder 13-14)
      Includes letters by Roger Baldwin, Sylvia Barrett, Robert Cantwell, Harry Dana, Floyd Dell, Theodore Dreiser, R. Palme Dutt, Irwin Edman, John Erskine, Waldo Frank, Sender Garlin, Lydia Gibson, Josephine Herbst, Rockwell Kent, Langston Hughes, Corliss Lamont, Max Lerner, Robert Morss Lovett, Scott Nearing, Clifford Odets, Isidor Schneider, George Seldes, Vincent Sheean, Upton Sinclair, John Strachey, Louis Untermeyer, Carl Van Doren, Mary Van Kleeck and others SEE ALSO: General/Correspondence/Farrar, John and Farrar and Rinehart, Inc.
    - Drafts (Box 73, Folder 1-8)
    - Drafts (Box 74, Folder 1-10)
    - Drafts (Box 75, Folder 1-6)
    - Draft fragments (Folder 7)
    - Notes and fragments (Folder 8)
    - Notes and fragments (Box 76, Folder 1-10)
    - Notes and fragments (Box 77, Folder 1-8)
    - Notes and fragments (Box 78, Folder 1-7)
      Includes material relating to Freeman's trip to Russia in 1926
    - Promotional material (Folder 8)
    - Reviews (Folder 9-10)
  - "The Third Candidate," Typescript, 1936 (Box 79, Folder 1)
  - "J. P. Morgan Loves His Country," New Masses, Typescript and printed copy, 1936 January 21 (Folder 2)
  - "Wilson's Ghost and Morgan's Power," New Masses, Typescript, letter, printed copy,and printed announcements of a debate with Gerald P. Nye, James J. McSwain and Freeman, 1936 January 28 (Folder 3)
  - Articles on chloride poisoning in General Electric plant in York, Pennsylvania, Daily Worker, (?) Typescripts, printed copy, letters, and miscellany, 1936, 1936 January 28-February 2 (Folder 4)
  - "Some American Communists," Partisan Review and Anvil, Excerpt from American Testament. Printed copy, 1936 February (Folder 5)
  - "'Fortune' and the Jews," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 February 4 (Folder 6)
  - "The Battle for Art," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 February 25 (Folder 7)
  - "Is Rome Ready for Peace?" New Masses, (attribution uncertain). Printed copy, 1936 March 10 (Folder 8)
  - "Revolutionary Research," New Masses, (attribution uncertain). Printed copy, 1936 March 17 (Folder 9)
  - Letter to the editor, Partisan Review and Anvil, (date written). Correction of errors relating to William F. Dunne contained in the article, "Some American Communists." Typescripts, 1936 March 23 (Folder 10)
  - "An Historic Opportunity," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 March 24. (Folder 11)
  - "McSwain, Disciple of Hearst," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 March 31. (Folder 12)
  - "The New World of Socialism," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 April 7. (Folder 13)
  - "The Two Danger Zones," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 April 14. (Folder 14)
  - "Thomas Jefferson," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 April 21. (Folder 15)
  - "Blood in Palestine," New Masses, (?) (attribution uncertain). Printed copy, 1936 April 26 (Folder 16)
  - "How Wilson Fought Lenin," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 April 28. (Folder 17)
  - "Labor Spies and Jew-Baiters," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 April 28. (Folder 18)
  - "Fifty May Days," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 May 5. (Folder 19)
  - "The President's Philosophy," New Masses, (attribution uncertain). Printed copy, 1936 May 5 (Folder 20)
  - "Ethiopia and World War," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 May 12. (Folder 21)
  - "Socialists Clean House," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 June 2. (Folder 22)
  - "The Socialists Hesitate," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 June 9. (Folder 23)
  - "John Reed," New Masses, Review of Granville Hicks, John Reed. Typescript, printed copy, flyer, and correspondence with Hicks and another, 1936 June 16 (Folder 24)
  - "The New Soviet Constitution," New Masses, (attribution uncertain). Printed copy, 1936 June 23 (Folder 25)
  - "The Republican Platform," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 June 23. (Folder 26)
  - "Who Backs the Black Legion?" New Masses, (attribution uncertain). Printed copy, 1936 June 30 (Folder 27)
  - "Tributes to Gorky," Soviet Russia Today, Printed copy, 1936 July. (Folder 28)
  - "Through Liberty to Socialism," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 July 7. (Folder 29)
  - "End the Black Legion," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 August 4. (Folder 30)
  - "Jew-Baiters," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 August 11. (Folder 31)
  - "The Middle Class and the Election," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 August 11. (Folder 32)
  - "Paging Mr. Winchell," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 August 11. (Folder 33)
  - "Lincoln Steffens," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 August 18. (Folder 34)
  - "Fourth-Estate Fascism," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 August 25 (Folder 35)
  - "The Muckraking Era," Pacific Weekly, Printed copy, 1936 August 31. (Folder 36)
  - "The Trotsky Cesspool," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 September 1. (Folder 37)
  - "High School Days," Pacific Weekly, Printed copy, 1936 September 7. (Folder 38)
  - "Defend the Ewerts!" New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 September 8 (Folder 39)
  - "The Kansas Trilby," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 September 8. (Folder 40)
  - "The Silk Hat," New Masses, ? Printed copy, 1936 September 15 (Folder 41)
  - "The Challenge and the Answer," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 September 15. (Folder 42)
  - "'Let Us Act Now!'" New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 September 22 (Folder 43)
  - "A Safe $5000 Offer," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 September 22. (Folder 44)
  - "Browder, Not Roosevelt," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 September 29. (Folder 45)
  - "The Progressive Vote," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 October 3. (Folder 46)
  - "A Warning to Liberals," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 October 6. (Folder 47)
  - Radio broadcast, Transcript, 1936 October 26. (Folder 48)
  - "Issues False and True," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 October 27. (Folder 49)
  - "Military 104," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 October 27. (Folder 50)
  - "Twenty-Five Years of America," New Order, Printed copy, 1936 November (Folder 51)
  - "How Not to Waste Your Ballot," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 November 3. (Folder 52)
  - "The Nation and Trotsky," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 November 10. (Folder 53)
  - "Now That Roosevelt's Elected ..." New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 November 10. (Folder 54)
  - "The Fate of Spain," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 November 17. (Folder 55)
  - "The Meaning of the Elections," New Masses, Typescript and printed copy, 1936 November 17. (Folder 56)
  - "The Stakes at Tampa," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 November 17. (Folder 57)
  - "The A.F. of L. Convention," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 December 1. (Folder 58)
  - "The Soviet Constitution," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 December 8. (Folder 59)
  - "Old Fervor and New Discipline," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 December 15. (Folder 60)
  - "People's Front," New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 December 15. (Folder 61)
  - "Once More the Nation, " New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 December 22. (Folder 62)
  - "Behind the Moscow Trial," Typescript (incomplete), 1936-1937 (Folder 63)
  - Editorials, New Masses, Printed copy, 1936 December 29-1937 January 19 (Folder 64)
  - "Karl Radek and Soviet Justice," New Masses, Galley proofs, 1937 Jan. 5. (Folder 65)
  - "As Congress Opens," New Masses, Printed copy, 1937 January 12. (Folder 66)
  - Radio speech, XEOF Radio (Mexico City), Typescripts (in English and Spanish), 1937 January 19 (Folder 67)
  - "A Letter from Mexico," Typescript, 1937 January 20. (Folder 68)
  - Interview, El Nacional, Typescript, 1937 January 21. (Folder 69)
  - "The Mexican Artist: 1937," Speech, First National Congress of the League of Mexican Writers and Artists. Typescripts (in English and Spanish), 1937 January 24. (Box 80, Folder 1)
  - "Letters from Laguna," Typescripts and letter, 1937, 1937 February (Folder 2)
  - "Artists in Action," New Masses, Typescript, related typescripts, and printed copy, 1937 February 2. (Folder 3)
  - "A Talk with Marcelino Domingo," Typescripts, 1937 March. (Folder 4)
  - Letter to the editor, New Republic, (date written). Response to comments by Edmund Wilson relating to the literary left. Typescript, letter to Malcolm Cowley, printed copy of Wilson's comments, and printed copy of related article by Cowley, 1937, 1937 March 1 (Folder 5)
  - "A Talk With Cardenas," New Masses, Interview with Lazaro Cardenas. Notes, typescripts, letter, and printed copies (in English and Spanish), 1937-1941, 1937 March 2. (Folder 6)
  - "Trotsky in Coyoacan," New Masses, Printed copy, 1937 March 23. (Folder 7)
  - Speech, Speech to a Young Communists League conference. Typescript, 1937 April 3. (Folder 8)
  - "Freeman vs. Wilson," New Republic, Letter to the editor in reply to comments by Edmund Wilson. Printed copy, printed copy of reply by Wilson, and letters to Malcolm Cowley and Wilson, 1937, 1937 April 21. (Folder 9)
  - "Cuba's Famous Exile," New Masses, Typescript and printed copy, 1937 May 9. (Folder 10)
  - Review of Reuben Osborn, Freud and Marx, Book Union Bulletin, Printed copy and correspondence with Osborn and another, 1937-1939, 1937 June. (Folder 11)
  - Speech, Speech to the League of American Writers' Conference, New York City. Typescript, 1937 June 6. (Folder 12)
  - Statement for the Tom Mooney Molders' Defense Committee, Letter and typescript, 1937, 1937 July 22. (Folder 13)
  - Statement for the anniversary of the Russian Revolution, Typescript and letter, 1937, 1937 October 25. (Folder 14)
  - Review of Leonard E. Mins (ed.), Engels on Capital, Typescript, 1937 November 2. (Folder 15)
  - Comment on debate between Theodore Dreiser and Clifford Barrett, "Have We Free Will?" (date written). Typescript, printed copy of Drieser-Barrett article, and correspondence, 1937-1938, 1937 November 29 (Folder 16)
  - "Ideas That Made Modern Literature," New Masses, Review of Mary M. Colum, From These Roots. Printed copy and letters, 1937 December 21 (Folder 17)
  - "Exclusive," (co-authored with George Albee?) Typescript play script., 1938 (Folder 18)
    SEE ALSO: CORRESPONDENCE/Albee, George and SPEECHES AND WRITINGS (PROSE)/ Correspondence/ Rollitts, Sarah
  - "Notes on Democracy and Literature," Typescript, 1938. (Folder 19)
  - "The Triumph of Time," Typescript play script, 1938. (Folder 20)
  - "Mexico Builds for the Future," Travel, Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence, 1937-1938, 1938 January (Folder 21)
  - "Edmund Wilson's Globe of Glass," New Masses, Typescripts and printed copy, 1938 April 12. (Box 81, Folder 1)
  - "Cedillo's Allies," New Masses, Printed copy, 1938 June 28. (Folder 2)
  - "Maurice Hindus' Personal History," New Masses, Review of Maurice Hindus, Green Worlds: An Informal Chronicle. Typescript and printed copy, 1938 September 6 (Folder 3)
  - "Arnold Reid," New Masses, Eulogy. Printed copy and letter, 1938, 1938 September 13. (Folder 4)
  - "Adventure Among the Masterpieces," Typescript, 1938 December (Folder 5)
  - "The Story of Democracy," Grant application material, typescripts (incomplete), and notes relating to ancient history, primarily Greece and Rome, 1938-1940 (Folder 6-10)
  - "The Forbidden Tree," Extensive autobiographical work, 1938-1964. (Folder 11)
    includes several fictionalized variants
    - General. Correspondence, outlines and introductory material
    - Drafts (in journal form)
      - 1938 January - 1940 October (Box 82, Folder 1-8)
      - 1940 November - 1947 March (Box 83, Folder 1-10)
      - 1947 April - August (Box 84, Folder 1-6)
      - 1947 September - November 15 (Box 85, Folder 1-6)
      - 1947 November 16 - 1948 February 4 (Box 86, Folder 1-5)
      - 1948 February 5 - March (Box 87, Folder 1-6)
      - 1948 April - December (Box 88, Folder 1-6)
      - 1949 January - May 6 (Box 89, Folder 1-6)
      - 1949 May 26 - August (Box 90, Folder 1-4)
      - 1949 September - 1950 May 19 (Box 91, Folder 1-5)
      - 1950 May 22 - 1951 April 11 (Box 92, Folder 1-6)
      - 1951 April 16 - 1952 November 2 (Box 93, Folder 1-6)
      - 1953 January 26 - December 30 (Box 94, Folder 1-5)
      - 1954 January - 1955 August 18 (Box 95, Folder 1-6)
      - 1955 August 19 - 1956 May (Box 96, Folder 1-5)
      - 1956 June - 1963 October (Box 97, Folder 1-6)
    - Notebooks, notes, and fragments
      - 1938-1946 (Box 98, Folder 1-5)
      - 1947 August - December 12 (Box 99, Folder 1-5)
      - 1947 December 12 - 1948 April (Box 100, Folder 1-6)
      - 1948 June - 1951 January 21 (Box 101, Folder 1-6)
      - 1951 January 21 - 1954 March 13 (Box 102, Folder 1-6)
      - 1954 March 15 - 1955 January 17 (Box 103, Folder 1-7)
      - 1955 January 17 - 1956 August 14 (Box 104, Folder 1-7)
      - 1956 August 14 - 1961 (Box 105, Folder 1-6)
      - 1962 - 1963 November 10 (Box 106, Folder 1-7)
      - 1963 November 10 - 1965 February (Box 107, Folder 1-7)
  - "An American Literary Heritage," Typescript, 1939. (Box 108, Folder 1)
  - "The Dream of Venus," Typescripts, 1939. (Folder 2)
  - "Fatherland," Proposed film script for Paul Massing. Typescript, 1939. (Folder 3)
  - "Marxist Criticism in America," Typescript, 1939 January - February (Folder 4)
  - "Coleridge and Wordsworth," New Masses, Typescript and printed copy, 1939 April 11. (Folder 5)
  - Speech, Speech to Writers' Conference, New School of Social Research, New York City. Typescripts, 1939 June 4. (Folder 6)
  - "The Democratic Idea, New Masses, Printed copy and letters, 1939 July 18. (Folder 7)
  - Letter to the editor, Nation, (date written). Reply to criticism by P. Dengel of Freeman's American Testament. Typescript drafts, printed copy of Dengel's comments, and notes relating to difficulties with other communists over the book, 1939 October 3 (Folder 8)
  - "The Prelude," Relates to the French Revolution and William Wordsworth. Typescript (incomplete), extensive notes, and bibliography, 1939-1951 (Folder 9-11)
  - Miscellaneous film proposals, Typescripts, circa 1940. (Box 109, Folder 1)
  - "On Rediscovering Milton," Notes for a biography of John Milton. Typescript notes, holographs, and letter to the Guggenheim Foundation, 1940, circa 1940. (Folder 2)
  - "Case History," Screenplay based on Sigmund Freud. Draft and final typescripts, outline, notes, clippings, miscellany, and correspondence with Irvin Shapiro and others, 1940 January, 1939-1958 (Folder 3-10)
  - Memorandum, Relates to Freeman's involvement in Partisan Review. Typescript, 1940 April 15 (Folder 11)
  - "Murder Monopoly," Nation, Projected series of articles relating to the prosecution of an organized crime syndicate by New York City District Attorney William O'Dwyer. Notes, clippings, draft typescripts, printed copy, memorandum, miscellany, and correspondence with Robert Bendiner, Cameron McKenzie, Richard Rovere, and others, 1940-1953, 1940 May 25. (Box 110, Folder 1-9)
  - "On 'The Irresponsibles,'" Nation, Comments on an article by Archibald MacLeish. Notes, typescript, printed copy, and letters to Robert Bendiner and another, 1940, 1940 June 1. (Folder 10)
  - "A Champion of Freedom," Relates to John Milton. Typescripts, 1940-1941. (Folder 11)
  - Testimony before the Coudert Committee, Summons, typescripts and clippings, 1940-1941, 1940 November - 1941 May. (Box 111, Folder 1)
  - "The Bible of Despots," Comments on Machiavelli, The Prince. Typescripts, 1941. (Folder 2)
  - "American Trade Unions and the Socialist Idea," Notes, typescript, and letter, 1941 (Folder 3)
  - Untitled statement relating to the German invasion of the Soviet Union, Typescript, 1941 August 11. (Folder 4)
  - "God Sees the Truth," Harpers, Typescripts, proofs, letters, biographical sketch, and invoice, 1940-1941, 1941 March. (Folder 5)
  - "The War and the Poets," Review of Oscar Williams, ed., New Poems, 1940: An Anthology of British and American Verse. Typescript, clippings, notes of interviews with Williams, and letters, 1940 - 1941 March 31 (Folder 6)
  - "Champion of Freedom," Typescript and letters, 1941, 1941 May. (Folder 7)
  - Review of Upton Sinclair, Between Two Worlds, Decision, July. Typescript, 1941 (Folder 8)
  - "Biographical Films," Typescripts, notes, clippings, galley proofs, and correspondence, 1939-1941, 1941 September (Folder 9)
  - "They Support the Soviet Union," Soviet Russia Today, Typescript, printed copy, and letters, 1941, 1941 September (Folder 10)